<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Venice looking-glasse: or, A letter vvritten very lately from London to Rome, by a Venetian Clarissimo to Cardinal Barberino, protector of the English nation, touching these present distempers. Wherein, as in a true mirrour, England may behold her owne spots, wherein she may see, and fore-see, her follies pass'd, her present danger, and furture destruction. Faithfully rendred out of the Italian into English.</title>
            <author>J. B. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C79A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E525_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864972</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864972</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117205</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81226)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117205)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 82:E525[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Venice looking-glasse: or, A letter vvritten very lately from London to Rome, by a Venetian Clarissimo to Cardinal Barberino, protector of the English nation, touching these present distempers. Wherein, as in a true mirrour, England may behold her owne spots, wherein she may see, and fore-see, her follies pass'd, her present danger, and furture destruction. Faithfully rendred out of the Italian into English.</title>
                  <author>J. B. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: J. B. C.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug ye 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117205:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Venice Looking-Glaſſe: OR, A LETTER VVRITTEN very lately from LONDON to ROME, by a <hi>Venetian Clariſsimo</hi> to Cardinal <hi>Barberino,</hi> Protector of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Nation, touching theſe preſent diſtempers.</p>
            <p>Wherein, as in a true <hi>Mirrour, ENGLAND</hi> may behold her owne ſpots, wherein ſhe may ſee, and <hi>fore-ſee,</hi> her Follies paſſ'd, her preſent Danger, and <hi>future</hi> Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Faithfully rendred out of the <hi>Jtalian</hi> into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Fas eſt, &amp; ab hoſte doceri.</q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117205:2"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO HIS COUNTRY.</head>
            <p>O <hi>England,</hi> (ſpecially thou beſotted City of <hi>London</hi>) if thou bee'ſt not paſt cure, or grown careleſſe and deſperat of thy ſelfe, be warn'd by this Stranger, who, having felt thy pulſe, and caſt thy water very exactly, diſcovers in thee ſymptomes of inevitable ruine. Divers of thy owne Children have oftentimes admoniſh'd thee with teares in their eyes, and terror in their hearts, to recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thy ſelfe, but they have been little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Let a <hi>Forreiners</hi> advice then take place, and make ſome impreſsions in thee, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent thy utter deſtruction.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117205:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS EMINENCE, THE LORD <hi>FRANCISCO BARBERINI,</hi> Cardinal of the moſt holy Apoſtolick See, and Protector of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, at his Palaces in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y laſt to your Eminence was but ſhort, in regard I had been but a ſhort time in this Countrey, I have now made a longer ſojourn here, and taken a lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely information of all matters; therefore I ſhal give your Eminence an account proportionably: For by converſation with the moſt indifferent, and intelligenc'd men, and by communication with the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors here reſident, I have taken ſome paines to pump out the truth of things.</p>
            <p>I find, that angry ſtar, which hath lowr'd ſo long upon <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117205:3"/>
in generall, hath been as predominant, and caſt as direfull aſpects upon this poor Iland, as upon any other part: Truly, my Lord, in all probability this people have paſſ'd the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of their happineſſe, and begin to decline extreamly, as well in <hi>Repute</hi> abroad, as alſo in the common notions of <hi>Religion,</hi> and indeed in the ordinary faculty of <hi>Reaſon:</hi> I think verily the Ill Spirit never reign'd ſo much in any corner of the earth by thoſe inhumane and horid things that I have obſerv'd among them, Nor is it a petty Spirit, but one of the greateſt Caco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daemons that thus drives them on, and makes them ſo active in the purſuance of their own perdition.</p>
            <p>To deduce matters from their Originall, Your Eminency may pleaſe to underſtand, that this King at his acceſſe to the Crown had deep debts to pay, both of His Fathers, and his own, he was left ingaged in a freſh warre with <hi>Spain;</hi> and had another preſently after with <hi>France,</hi> and both at one time, but he came off well enough of thoſe: Afterwards never any Countrey flouriſhed in that envied happineſſe, and wanton kind of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; This City of <hi>London</hi> was grown to be the greateſt Mart, and miſtreſſe of Trade, of any in the world, Inſomuch, as I have been certainly inform'd, the King might have eaten meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon His cuſtomes 4000 crownes a day: Moreover, ſhe had a vaſt bank of money being made the <hi>ſcale</hi> of conveying the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> treaſure to <hi>Flanders:</hi> Inſomuch that in a few yeers ſhe had above ten millions of his moneys brought hither, which ſhe might have remitted in <hi>ſpecie</hi> or in marchandize, and for which this King had five in the hundred for coynage: Yet could he not get beforehand with the world, having a ſiſter with ſo many Nephews and neeces, having a Queen with diverſe children of His own, (at leaſt 16 of the Blood-Royall) to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, with divers profuſe Courtiers beſides, which made Him more parſimonious then ordinary. The Warres then growing more active 'twixt <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as alſo 'twixt <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> both by Land and Sea, and divers great Fleets of Men
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117205:3"/>
of War as well <hi>French</hi> (who were growne powerfull that way) as <hi>Dunkerkers, Spaniards, Hollanders,</hi> and <hi>Hamburgers,</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring daily in His narrow Seas, and ſayling cloſe by His <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> the world wondred this King had no greater ſtrength at Sea, in caſe that any of the foreſaid Nations ſhould doe him an affront, as ſome of them had already done, by denying to daſh their Colours to His Ships: Inſomuch that in <hi>Holland</hi> and other places he was paſquill'd at, and pourtrayed lying in his cradle lullaby'd and rock'd aſleep by the Spaniard: Hereupon being by advertiſements from His Agents abroad, and frequent advice of His Privie Councell at home, made ſenſible of the danger, and a kind of diſhonour he was falne into, and having intelligence that the French Cardinall began to queſtion his title to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Narrow Seas, conſidering He employed no viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power to preſerve it, He began to conſult of meanes to ſet forth a Royall Fleet: but in regard the Purſe of the Crowne was lightly ballaſted, and that he had no mind to ſummon the three Eſtates, becauſe of ſome indignities he had received in former Parliaments by the <hi>Puritan</hi> party, (a race of people averſe to all Kingly Government, unleſſe they may pare it as they pleaſe) his then Atturney Generall, a great cryed-up-Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, put it in his Head to impoſe an old Tax called <hi>Ship-mony</hi> upon the Subject, which the ſaid Lawyer did warrant upon his life to be Legall, for he could produce diverſe Records how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Progenitors had done the like: The King not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with his ſingle opinion, referred it to His Learned Councell, and they unanimouſly averred it to be agreeable to the Law of the Land; yet this would not fully ſatisfie the King, but He would have the Opinion of His twelve Judges, and <hi>they</hi> alſo affirmed by their ſeverall vouches the ſaid Tax to be warrantable; Hereupon it was impoſed and leavied, but ſome refuſing to pay it, there was a ſuite commenc'd, during which all the Judges were to re-deliver their opinions joyntly, and the buſineſſe being maturely debated and canvaſed in open
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117205:4"/>
Court divers months, and all arguments produc'd <hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> nine of the ſaid twelve Judges concluded it Legal: Thereupon the King continued the impoſition of the ſaid Tax, and never was money imployed ſo much for the Honour and advantage of a Countrey, for he ſent out every Summer a Royall fleet to ſcowre and ſecure the Seas; he cauſed a Galeon to be built, the greateſt and gallanteſt that ever ſpread ſaile: Nor did he purſe up, and diſpoſe of one peny of this money to any other uſe, but added much of his own Revenues yeerly thereunto: So the world abroad cried up the King of <hi>England</hi> to be awake againe; <hi>Trade</hi> did wonderfully encreaſe, both Domeſtic and forrein in all the three Kingdomes; <hi>Ireland</hi> was reduced to an abſolute Settlement, the Arreares of the Crown payed, and a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Revenue came thence cleerly to the Exchequer of <hi>England</hi> every year, the ſalaries of all Officers, with the pay of the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Army there, and all other Charges being defrayed by <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> her ſelf, which was never done before. Yet for all this height of happineſſe, and the glorious fruites of the ſaid Ship-money, (which was but a kind of petty inſenſible Tax, &amp; a thing of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to what hath happened ſince) there were ſome fooliſh people in this Land which murmured at it, and cryed out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a Parliament, a Parliament; and they have had one ſince with a vengeance.</p>
            <p>But before this occaſion, it was obſerved, that the ſeedes of diſobedience, and a ſpirit of inſurrection was a long time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendring in the hearts of ſome of this peace-pampred People, which is conceived to proceed from their converſation and comerce with three ſorts of men, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Scot,</hi> the <hi>Hollander</hi> and the <hi>French Huguenot.</hi> Now an advantage happened that much conduced to neceſſitate the convoking of a Parliament, which was an ill-favoured traverſe that fell out in <hi>Scotland;</hi> For the King intending an Uniformity of Divine worſhip in all His three Kingdomes, ſent thither the <hi>Lyturgie</hi> of this Church, but it found cold and coorſe entertainment there, for the whole
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117205:4"/>
Nation, men, women and children riſe up againſt them: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the King abſolutely revoked it by Proclamation, wherein He declared 'twas never His purpoſe to preſſe the practice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon the Conſciences of any; therefore commanded that all things ſhould be in <hi>ſtatu quo prius,</hi> but this would not ſerve the turn, the <hi>Scot</hi> took advantage hereby to deſtroy <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> and pull down Biſhops to get their demeanes: To which purpoſe they came with an Army in open Field againſt their own Native King, who not diſgeſting this indignity, Muſtred another <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Army; which being upon the confines of both Kingdomes, a kind of Pacification was plaiſtred over for the preſent. The King returning to <hi>London,</hi> and conſulting His ſecond thoughts, reſented that inſolency of the <hi>Scots</hi> more then formerly: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon He ſummons a Parliament, and deſires aid to Vindicat that Affront of the <hi>Scot.</hi> The <hi>Scot</hi> had ſtrong Intelligence with the Puritan Faction in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, who ſeemed to abet his quarell, rather then to be ſenſible of any nationall diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour received from him; which cauſed that ſhort-lived Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſſolve in diſcontent, and the King was forced to finde other meanes to raiſe and ſupport an Army by private Loanes of His Nobler ſort of Subjects and Servants: The <hi>Scot</hi> having punctuall Advertiſments of every thing that paſſed, yea, in the Kings Cabinet Councell was not idle all this while, but rallies what was left of the former Army (which by the articles of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification ſhould have been abſolutely diſmiſſed) and boldly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades <hi>England,</hi> which he durſt never have done, if he had not well known that this Puritan Party which was now grown very powerfull here, and indeed had invited him to this expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, would ſtand to him. This forrein Army being, by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious cloſe machinations of ſome mongrell <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, entred into the Bowels of the Country, the King was forced to call this preſent Parliament, with whom he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in every thing, ſo far as to ſacrifice unto them both Judge, Biſhop, Councellor and Courtier; yea, He yeilded to the tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling down of many tribunalls of Juſtice, which were an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117205:5"/>
to his Prerogative; He aſſented that the Prelates, who were the moſt Ancient and Prime Members of the upper Houſe, and had priority of all others, ſince the firſt conſtitution of Parliament in the enrollment of all Acts, He aſſented I ſay that theſe, who were the greateſt prop of His Crown ſhould be quite outed from among the Peers; He granted them alſo a <hi>Trienniall</hi> Parliament, and after that, this <hi>Perpetuall;</hi> which words, to the apprehenſion of any rationall man, carry with them a groſſe abſurdity in the very ſenſe of the thing: And touching this laſt Grant, I had it from a good hand, that the Queen was a friend to this Parliament, and your Eminence knowes how they have requited Her ſince, but the maine open Councellor to this fatall Act was a <hi>Scot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the reaſon which they alledged for this everlaſting Parliament was one of the baldeſt that ever I heard of, it was, that they might have time enough to pay the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, whereas in one morning they might have diſpatched that, by paſſing ſo many Subſidies for that uſe, and upon the credit of thoſe, they might have raiſed what money they would.</p>
            <p>The Parliament finding the King ſo pliable, and His pulſe to beat ſo gently, like ill-natur'd men they fall from inches to ells in ſeeking their advantages: They grew ſo peremptory as to demand all the military ſtrength of the Kingdom, the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> with the whole Royall Navy, which they found in an excellent equipage, gramercy ſhipmony; ſo that the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Ship-mony, which they ſo clamoured at, turned moſt to their advantage of any thing afterwards.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scot</hi> being Fidler-like returned to his Country with meat, drink, and mony, the King went a while after to keep a Parliament there, wherein he filled every blank, they did but ask and have, for He granted them what poſſibly they could propound, both for their Kirk and State, many received Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and they divided Biſhops Lands amongſt them: for all which unparallel'd Conceſſions of Princely grace, they cauſed an Act already in force to be publiſhed, <hi>viZ.</hi> that it ſhould be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117205:5"/>
damnable Treaſon in the higheſt degree that could be, for any of the Scots Nation conjunctly or ſingly to levy armes, or any mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Forces, upon any pretext whatſoever, without His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties royall Commiſſion; and this they caus'd to be don by way of gratitude, but how they perform'd it afterwards the world knowes too well.</p>
            <p>The King returning to <hi>London,</hi> in lieu of a wellcom to his two Houſes of Parliament (to whom alſo before his departure he had paſſed more Acts of Grace then all his Progenitors, take them all in a lump) they had patch'd up a kind of <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> which was voted in the dead of night, wherein they expos'd to the world the leaſt moat in former government, and aggravated to the very height every grievance, all which the King had redreſſed before; and this <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> which breath'd nothing but a baſe kind of malice, they preſented as a noſegay to their Soverain Prince, to congratulate his ſafe return from a forren Countrey; which they caus'd to be printed &amp; publiſh'd before he could give any anſwer thereunto. The King finding ſuch a viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpirit ſtill raign in the Houſe, and knowing who were chiefly poſſeſs'd with it (whom he had impeach'd before, but ſaw he could get no juſtice againſt them) in ſuch an extremity, he did an act like a generous Prince, for taking the <hi>Palſgrave</hi> with him, he took the firſt coach he met withall at his Court gate, and went to his Houſe of Commons in perſon to demand five Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which he wold prove to be Traitors in the higheſt degree, and to be the Authors of all theſe diſtempers, proteſting upon the word of a King, that they ſhold have as fair &amp; legall a tryall as ever men had; in the interim he only deſir'd that their perſons might be ſecur'd: The walls of both Houſes, and the very ſtones in London ſtreet did ſeem to ring of this high cariage of the Kings, and the ſound went thence to the Countrey, whence the ſilly Plebeians came preſently in whole heards to this City, and ſtrowting up and down the ſtreets, had nothing in their mouths, but that the priviledg of Parlement, the priviledg of Parlement was broken, though it be the known cleer Law of the Land, that the Parlement cannot ſuperſede or ſhelter any treaſon.</p>
            <p>The King finding how violently the pulſe of the gr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſly ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced people did beat, and there having been formerly divers rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117205:6"/>
crues of baſe Mechaniques and Mariners, who had affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both his own Court, and the two Houſes beſides, which the Commons, to their eternall reproach, conniv'd at, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that divers motions were made by the Lords to ſuppreſſe them, the King alſo having private intelligence that there was a miſchievous plot to ſurprize his perſon, remov'd his Court to the Countrey.</p>
            <p>The King departing, or rather being <hi>driven</hi> away thus from his two Houſes, by this mutinous City, he might well at his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away have obraided her in the ſame words as <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. did upbraid <hi>Paris,</hi> who being by ſuch another tumultuous rabble driven out of her in the time of the <hi>Ligue,</hi> as he was loſing ſight of her, he turn'd his face back, and ſayed, <hi>Farewell ingratefull Cittie, I will never ſee thee again till I make my way into thee through thy Walls:</hi> Yet, though the King abſented himſelf in perſon thus from the two Houſes, he ſent them frequent meſſages, that they wold draw into Acts what he had already aſſented unto, and if any thing was left yet undon by him, he wold do it; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will'd them to leave off thoſe groundles feares and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies wherwith they had amus'd both Cittie and Countrey; and he was ready to return at all times to his Palace in Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, provided that his Perſon might be ſecur'd from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer barbariſms &amp; outrages: But in lieu of a dutifull compliance with their Prince, the thoughts of the two Houſes ran upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but war: The King then retiring into the North, &amp; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a few of his ſervants only to go viſit a Town of his, he was denied entrance by a fatall unlucky wretch, who afterwards was ſhamefully executed, with his eldeſt ſon, by command of his new Maſters of the Parlement: The King being thus ſhut out of his own town (which open'd the firſt dore to a bloudy war) put forth a Declaration, wherein he warn'd all his people that they ſhould look to their proprieties, for if <hi>Hee</hi> was thus barr'd of his owne, how could any private Subject be ſure to be Maſter of any thing he had, and herein he was as much <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> as <hi>Prince;</hi> For the Parlement-men afterwards made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfs Land-Lords of the whole Kingdome, it hath been uſuall for them to thruſt any out of his freehold, to take his bed from under him, and his ſhirt from off his very back. The King being
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117205:6"/>
kept thus out of one of his townes, might well ſuſpect that he might be driven out of another, therefore 'twas time for him to look to the preſervation of his Perſon, and the Countrey came in voluntarily unto him by thouſands to that purpoſe, but hee made choice of a few only to be his gard, as the Parlement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers had don a good while before for themſelfs: But now they went otherwiſe to worke, for they fell a levying, liſting, and arming men by whole Regiments and Brigades till they had a verie conſiderable Army a foot, before the King had one Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queteer or Trooper on his ſide: yet theſe men are ſo notorious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impudent, as to make the King the firſt Aggreſſor of the war, and to lay upon Him all the blood that was ſpilt to this day, wherein the Devill himſelf cannot be more ſhameles. The Parliamenteers having an army of foot and horſe thus in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Equipage, 'twas high time for the King to look to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, therefore he was forced to diſplay his royall Standard, and draw his ſword quite out: Thus a cruell and moſt cruentous civill war began which laſted neer upon foure yeers without intermiſſion, wherin there happen'd more battailes, ſieges and skirmiſhes, then paſſed in the Netherlands in foureſcore yeers, and herein the Engliſhmen may be ſaid to get ſom credit abroad in the world, that they have the ſame blood running in their veines (though not the ſame braines in their ſculls) which their Anceſtors had, who were obſerved to be the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt peeple in the field, impatient of delay, and moſt deſirous of battaile then any Nation.</p>
            <p>But it was one of the greateſt miracles that ever happen'd in this Land how the King was able to ſubſiſt ſo long againſt the Parlamenteers, conſidering the multiplicity of infinite advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages they had of him by water and land: for they had the <hi>Scot,</hi> the <hi>Sea</hi> and the <hi>City</hi> on their ſide; touching the firſt, he ruſhed in as an Auxiliary, with above 20000. Horſe and Foot compleatly furniſh'd both with ſmall and great ammunition and arms, well cloth'd and money'd: For the ſecond, they had all the Kings Ships well appointed, which are held to be the greateſt ſecurity of the Iſland both for defence and offence, for every one of them is accounted one of the moving Caſtles of the Kingdome: beſides they had all the other ſtanding ſtone-Caſtles,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117205:7"/>
Forts, and tenable places to boot: Concerning the laſt, (viz. the City) therein they had all the wealth, bravery, and prime ammunition of England, this being the onely Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin of men and money: Now if the King had had but one of theſe on his ſide, he had in all probability cruſh'd them to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: yet did he bear up ſtrangely againſt them a long time, and might have don longer, had he kept the campane, and not ſpent the ſpirits of his men before Townes; had he not made a diſadvantagious election of ſom Commanders in chief, and laſtly, had he not had cloſe <hi>Traitors</hi> within dores, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <hi>Rebells</hi> without; for his very Cabinet Councell, and Bed-Chamber were not free of ſuch vermin, and herein the Parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteers ſpent unknown ſums and were very prodigall of the Kingdomes money.</p>
            <p>The King, after many traverſes of war, being reduced to a great ſtreight by croſſe ſucceſſes and Counſells, rather then to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the Parlementeers, withdrew himſelfe in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingmans diſguiſe to the Scors army, as his laſt randevous, and this plott was manag'd by the French Agent then reſiding here; A man wold think that that Nation wol'd have deem'd it an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall honor unto them to have their own King and Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man throw himſelf thus into their armes, and to repoſe ſuch a ſingular truſt in them upon ſuch an Extremity: but they corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponded not ſo well with him as he expected, for though at firſt when the Parlamenteers ſollicited their <hi>deer Brethren</hi> for a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Kings perſon unto them, their note was then, if any forren petty Prince had ſo put himſelf upon them, they could not with honor deliver him, much leſſe their own Native King; yet they made a ſacrifice of him at laſt for 800000. Crownes; whereupon <hi>Bellieure</hi> the French Ambaſſador being convoyed by a Troop of horſe from the King towards London, to ſuch a ſtand, in lieu of larges to the ſouldiers, he drew out an halfe crown peece, and asked them how many pence that was, they anſwered 30. <hi>He replied, for ſo much did Judas betray his Maſter, and ſo he departed</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, that in the cours of this Hiſtoricall Narration I have touch'd upon <hi>France,</hi> your Eminence may pleaſe to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that nothing allmoſt could tend more to the advantage of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117205:7"/>
that King, then theſe commotions in England, conſidering that he was embark'd in an actuall war with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and that this Iland did do <hi>Spain</hi> ſom good offices; among other, by tranſport of his treaſure to Dunkerk in Engliſh bottomes, wherunto this King gave way, and ſomtimes in his own Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which ſav'd the Spainard neer upon 20. in the hundred, then if he had ſent it by way of Genoa; ſo that ſom think, though France made ſemblance to reſent the ſad condition of her Neighbour, and thereupon ſent the Prince of <hi>Harcour,</hi> and the foreſaid Monſieur <hi>Bellieure</hi> to compoſe matters, yet ſhe never really intended it, as being againſt her preſent intereſt and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements: yet the world thinks it much that ſhe ſhold pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely receive an Agent from theſe Parlamenteers, and that the French Nobility who were us'd to be the gallanteſt men in the world to vindicate the quarrels of diſtreſſed Ladies, are not more ſenſible of the outrages that have bin offer'd a daughter of France, ſpecially of <hi>Henry the great's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to reſume the threed of my Narration, the King (and with him, one may ſay, England alſo) being thus bought and ſold, the Parlamenteers inſteed of bringing him to Weſtminſter, which had put a Period to all diſtempers toſs'd him up and downe to private houſes, and kept the former Army ſtill a foot: And truly I think there was never Prince ſo abus'd, or poor pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo baffled, and no peeple but a purblind beſotted peeple wold have ſuffred themſelfs to be ſo baffled: for notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that no Enemy appeer'd in any corner of the Kingdom, yet above 20000. Tagaroons have bin kept together ever ſince to grind the faces of the poore, and exhauſt the very vitall ſpirits of town and Countrey, and keep them all in a perfect ſlavery: Had the Parlement-men, when the Scots were gone, brought their King in a generous and frank way (as had well becom'd Engliſhmen) to ſitt among them, and truſted to him (which of neceſſity they muſt do at laſt) as they had gain'd more honor far in the world abroad, ſo they had gain'd more upon his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections then I beleeve they will ever do hereafter.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, the King having bin a good while priſoner to the Parlement, the Army ſnatch'd him away from them, and ſom of the chiefeſt Commanders having pawn'd their ſoules un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117205:8"/>
him to reſtore him ſpeedily, in lieu thereof they tumbled him up and down to ſundry places, till they juggled him at laſt to that ſmall Ile where now he is ſurrounded with a gard of ſtrange faces and if happly he beginns to take delight in any of thoſe faces, he is quickly taken out of his ſight. Theſe harſh uſages hath made him becom all gray and oregrown with hair, ſo that he lookes rather like ſom Silvan Satyr then a Soverain Prince: And truly my Lord the meaneſt ſlave in St. <hi>Marks</hi> gallies or the abiect's Captif in <hi>Algier</hi> bannier is not ſo miſerable as he in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers kinds, for <hi>they</hi> have the comfort of their wifes, children and frends, they can convey and receive Letters, ſend Meſſeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers upon their errands, and have privat diſcours with any; all which is denied to the King of great Britain, nay the young Princes his children are not permitted as much as to ask him bleſſing in a letter. In ſo much that if he were not a great King of his paſſions, and had a heart caſt in an extraordinary Mould, theſe preſſures &amp; thoſe baſe aſperſions that have bin publiquely caſt upon him by the Parlement it ſelf, had bin enough to have ſent him out of the world e're this, and indeed 'tis the main thing they drive at, to torture his brain, and tear his very heartſtrings if they could: ſo that wheras this fooliſh ignorant peeple ſpeak ſuch horrid things of our <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> truly my Lord 'tis a moſt gentle way of proceeding being compar'd to this Kings perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>As the King himſelfe is thus in quality of a captif, ſo are all his Subjects becom perfect ſlaves, they have fool'd themſelfs into a worſe ſlavery then <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Greek</hi> under the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> for they know the bottom of their ſervitude by paying ſo many Sultaneſſes for every head; but here, peeple are put to endles, unknowne, tyrannicall Taxes, beſides <hi>plundring</hi> and <hi>AcciZe,</hi> which two words, and the practiſe of them (with <hi>ſtorming</hi> of Townes) they have learnt of their pure brethren of Holland: and for <hi>plundrings,</hi> theſe Parlementeer Saints think they may robb any that adheres not to them as lawfully as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did the <hi>Egiptians:</hi> 'Tis an unſommable maſſe of money theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers have ſquandred in few yeers, whereof they have often promis'd and ſolemnly voted a publike account to ſatisfie the Kingdome: but as in a hundred things more, ſo in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117205:8"/>
particular they have diſpens'd with their Votes: they have conſumed more treaſure with pretence to <hi>purge</hi> one Kingdome, then might have ſerved to have <hi>purchas'd</hi> two; more (as I am credibly told) then all the Kings of England ſpent of the public ſtock ſince the <hi>Saxon</hi> Conqueſt: Thus have they not only beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd the whole Iland, but they have hurld it into the moſt fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full'ſt Chaos of confuſion that ever poore Countrey was in; they have torne in pieces the reines of all Government, trampled upon all Lawes of heaven and earth, and violated the very Dictamens of nature, by making mothers to betray their ſonnes, and the ſonnes their fathers, but ſpecially that great <hi>Charter,</hi> which is the <hi>Pandect</hi> of all the Lawes and Liberties of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Subject, which at their admiſſion to the Houſe they are ſolemnly ſworn to maintaine, is torn in flitters: beſides thoſe ſeverall Oaths they forg'd themſelfs, as the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> where they voluntarily ſweare to maintain the Kings Honor and Rights, together with the eſtabliſhed Lawes of the Land, &amp;c. Now I am told, that all Acts of Parlement here are Lawes, and they carry that Majeſtie with them, that no power can ſuſpend or repeale them, but the ſame power that made them, which is the King ſitting in full Parlement; theſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grell Polititians have bin ſo notoriouſly impudent as to make an inferior <hi>Ordinance</hi> of theirs to do it, which is point-blank a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the very fundamentalls of this Government, and their owne Oaths, which makes me think that there was never ſuch a perjur'd pack of wretches upon earth, never ſuch Monſters of mankind.</p>
            <p>Yet this ſimple infatuated peeple have a Saint-like opinion of theſe Monſters, this fooliſh Citie gards them daily with Horſe and Foot, whereby ſhe may be ſayd to kiſſe the very ſtones that are thrown at her, and the hand whence they came, which a dogg wold not do: But ſhe falls to recollect her felf now that ſhe begins to be pinch'd in Trade, that that her <hi>Mint</hi> is ſtarv'd, and that the Prince commands both Sea and River: yet the leading'ſt men in her Common-Councell care not much for it, in regard moſt of them have left traffiqueing abroad, finding it a more eaſie and gainefull way of trading at home, by purchaſing Church-lands, plunder'd goods, and debts upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117205:9"/>
the <hi>Public Faith;</hi> thus the Saints of this Iland <hi>turn godlineſſe into gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly my Lord, I give the Engliſh for a loſt Nation, never was there a more palpable oblaeſion of the brain, and a more viſible decay of reaſon in any race of men: it is a ſtrange judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from heaven, that a peeple ſhold not be more ſenſible how they are becom ſlaves to Rebells, and thoſe moſt of them the ſcumm of the Nation, which is the baſeſt of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: how they ſuffer them to tyrannize by a meer arbitrary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trajudiciall power o're their very ſoules and bodies, o're their very lifes and livelihoods; how their former freedom is turn'd to fetters, Molehills into Mountaines of grievances, <hi>Ship-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> into <hi>Accize,</hi> Juſtice into Tyranny: For nothing hath bin and is daily ſo common amongſt them as impriſonment with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out charge, and a charge without an accuſer, condemnation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out apparance, and forfaitures without conviction.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak a little more of the King, if all the infernall fiends had ligu'd againſt him, they could not have deſignd &amp; diſgorg'd more malice: they wold have laid to his charge his fathers death, as arrand a lie as ever was hatch'd in hell: they wold make him fore-know the inſurrection in Ireland, whereas the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador here, &amp; his Confeſſor who is a very reverend Iriſh man, told me, that he knew no more of it then the grand <hi>Mogor</hi> did: they charge him with all the bloud of this civill warre, wheras they and their inſtruments were the firſt kindlers of it, and that firſt prohibited trade: they intercepted and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his privat letters to his Queen, and hers to him, (Oh barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous baſeneſſe!) but therin they did him a pleaſure, though the intent was malitious, their aym in all things being to imbitter and envenom the hearts of his peeple towards him; and this was to render him a glorious and well-belov'd Prince, and for making him rich, all which they had vow'd to do upon paſſing the Act of Continuance, they have made him poorer then the meaneſt of all his vaſſalls, they have made him to have no propriety in houſe, goods, or Lands, or as one may ſay, in his wife and children: 'Twas uſuall for the father to hunt in his Park while the ſon hunted for his life in the field, for the wife to lye in his bedds, while the husband layed wait to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117205:9"/>
murther him abroad; they have ſeiz'd upon and ſold his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Hangings and Plate, yea his very Cabinets, Jewells and Pictures.</p>
            <p>Nor are they the honorableſt ſort of peeple, and men nobly extracted (as in Scotland) that do all this, (for then it were not ſo much to be wondred at) but they are the meaneſt ſort of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, many of them Mechaniques, whereof the lower Houſe is full; ſpecially the ſubordinate Committees, who domineer more ore Nobles and Gentry, then the Parliament-Members themſelfs their Maſters.</p>
            <p>Touching thoſe few Peers that ſit now voting in the upper Houſe, they may be ſayed to be but mee<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cyphers, they are grown ſo degenerate as to ſuffer the <hi>Commons</hi> to give them the Law, to ride upon their backs, and do moſt things without them: There be many thouſand Petitions that have been recommended by theſe Lords to the lower Houſe, which are ſcornfully thrown into corners and never read; their Meſſengers have us'd to dance attendance divers houres and dayes afore they were vouchſafed to be let in or heard, to the eternall diſhonor of thoſe Peers, and yet poor ſpirited things they reſent it not: The Commons now command all, and though, as I am inform'd, they are ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd thither by the Kings Originall Writt but to <hi>conſent</hi> to what the King and his great Counſell of Peers (which is the true Court of Parlement) ſhall reſolve upon; They are now from <hi>Conſenters</hi> becom the chiefeſt <hi>Counſellors</hi> yea <hi>Controw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> of all; nay ſom of this lower Houſe fly ſo high as to term themſelfs <hi>Conquerors,</hi> and though in all conferences with the Lords <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſtand bare before them, yet by a new way of mix'd Committees they cary themſelfs as <hi>Collegues:</hi> Theſe are the men that now have the vogue, and they have made their Priviledges ſo big ſwoln, that they ſeem to have quite ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up both the Kings Prerogatives, and that of the Lords: Theſe are the Grandees, and <hi>Sages</hi> of the times, though moſt of them have but crack'd braines and crazy fortunes; Nay ſom of them are ſuch arrand Knaves and coxcombs, that 'tis queſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble whither they more want common honeſty, or common ſenſe; nor know no more what belongs to true policy then the left legg of a joint-ſtoole: They are grown ſo high a tiptoes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117205:10"/>
that they ſeem to ſcorn an Act of Amneſtia<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or any grace from their King, wheras ſom of them deſerve to be hang'd as oft as they have haires upon their heads; nor have they any more care of the common good of <hi>England</hi> then they have of <hi>Lapland,</hi> ſo they may ſecure their perſons, and continue their Power and Authority, is ſweet, though it be in Hell. Thus, my Lord, is England now govern'd, ſo that 'tis an eaſy thing to take a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her ruine; The Scot is now the riſing man, who is the third time ſtruck into her bowells with a numerous Army: They ſay he hath vow'd never to return till he hath put the Crown on the Kings head, the Scepter in his hand, and the ſword by his ſide; if he do ſo, it will be the beſt thing that ever he did, though ſom think that he will never be able to do Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land as much good as he hath don her hurt; He hath extremely outwitted the Engliſh of late yeers: And they who were the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of his firſt and laſt coming in, I hold to be the moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Enemies that ever this Nation had; for 'tis probable that <hi>Germany</hi> will be ſooner free of the <hi>Swed,</hi> then <hi>England</hi> of the <hi>Scot,</hi> who will ſtick cloſe unto him like a burr, that he cannot ſhake him off; He is becom allready Maſter of the Engliſhmans ſoul, by impoſing a religion upon him, and he may hereafter be maſter of his body.</p>
            <p>Your Eminence knowes there is a periodicall fate hangs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all Kingdoms after ſuch a revolution of time, and rotation of fortunes wheele; the cours of the world hath bin, for one Nation, like ſo many nailes, to thruſt out another; But for this Nation, I obſerve by conference with divers of the ſaddeſt and beſt weighdſt men among them, that the ſame preſages foretell their ruine as did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old, which was a murmuring againſt their Governors; It is a long time that both <hi>Judges Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>privy Counſellors</hi> have bin mutter'd at, wherof the firſt ſhold be the oracles of the <hi>Law,</hi> the other of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the laſt of <hi>State-affaires,</hi> and that our judgments ſhold acquieſce upon theirs; Here as I am inform'd; 'twas common for evry ignorant client to arraign his Judg; for evry puny Clerk to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Biſhop; for evry ſhallow-brain home-bred fellow to deſcant upon the reſults of the Councell Table: and this ſpirit of contradiction and contumacy hath bin a long time foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117205:10"/>
in the minds of this peeple, infus'd into them principally, by the Puritanicall Faction. Touching the ſecond of theſe (I mean Biſhops) they are grown ſo odious (principally for their large demeanes) among this peeple, as <hi>Monks</hi> were of old, and one may ſay it is a juſt judgment fallen upon them, for they were moſt buſy in demoliſhing <hi>Convents</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> as theſe are in deſtroying <hi>Cathedralls</hi> and <hi>Ministers;</hi> But above all, it hath bin obſerv'd that this peeple hath bin a long time rotten-hearted towards the ſplendor of the Court, the very glory of their King, and the old eſtabliſh'd Government of the land: 'Tis true there were a few ſmall leakes ſprung in the great veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the State, (and what veſſell was ever ſo tite but was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to leakes?) but theſe wiſeakers in ſtopping of one have made a hundred: Yet if this Kings raign were parallell'd to that of Queen <hi>EliZabeth's,</hi> who was the greateſt Minion of a peeple that ever was, one will find that ſhe ſtretch'd the Prerogative as much: In her time as I have read in the Latin Legend of her life, ſom had their hands cut off for writing againſt her matching with the Duke of <hi>Aniou,</hi> others were hang'd at Tyburn for tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing her government; ſhe pardon'd thrice as many Roman Prieſts as this King did ſhe paſſ'd divers Monopolies, ſhe kept an Agent at Rome, ſhe ſent her Sargeant at Armes to pluck out a Member then ſitting in the Houſe of Commons by the eares, and clap'd him in priſon; ſhe call'd them ſawcy fellowes to meddle with her <hi>Prerogative,</hi> or with the government of her houſhold, ſhe mannag'd all forren affaires, ſpecially the warrs with <hi>Ireland</hi> ſoly by her privy Counſell; yet there was no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring at her raign, and the reaſon I conceave to be, that there was neither Scot or Puritan had then any ſtroke in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, for all their diſobedience and grumblings againſt their Liege Lord the King, this peeple are exactly obedient to their new Maſters of the Houſe of Commons, though they ſit there but as their <hi>Servants</hi> and entitle themſelfs ſo; and alſo though in lieu of the ſmall ſcratches which England might happily have receiv'd before (all which the King had cur'd) theſe new Maſters have made ſuch deep gaſhes in her, and given her ſuch deadly wounds, that I believe are incurable.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I find by my reſearches, that there are two great
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117205:11"/>
Idolls in this Kingdome the greateſt that ever were, they are the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> 'tis held a kind of blaſphemy, if not a ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt to ſpeak againſt the one, and the whole body of Religion is nailed unto the other, for there is no devotion here at all but preaching, which God wot is little better then prating. The abuſe of theſe two hath bin the ſource of all the diſtempers which now raign: touching the latter, it hath ſerv'd as a ſubſervient Engin to prop up the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and popularity of the firſt; theſe malicious Pulpit-men breath out nothing thence but either ſedition, ſchiſme or blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy: poor ſhallow brain'd Scioliſts, they wold queſtion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things in the old Teſtament, and find Apocrypha in the New: And ſuch is the violence wherewith the minds of men and women are tranſported towards theſe Preachmen, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of devotion beſides, that in all probability they will in time take a ſurfet of them: ſo that give this giddy peeple line enough there will be no need of <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>holique</hi> Arms to reduce them to the Apoſtolic Church, they will in time pave the way to it themſelves, and be glad to return to <hi>Rome</hi> to find out a Religion again.</p>
            <p>There was here before, as I am informed, a kind of a face of a Church, there were ſome ſolemnities, venerations and decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies us'd that a man might diſcover ſome piety in this peeple; there was a publick Liturgie that in pithy Patheticall prayers reach'd all occaſions; the Sacraments were adminiſtred with ſome reverence, their Churches were kept neat and comly; but this <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſty race of miſcreants have nothing at all of ſweetneſſe, of piety and devotion in them; 'tis all turn'd to a fatuous kind of more zeal after learning, as if Chriſtianity had no ſobriety, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, or end of knowledg at all: Theſe ſilly things, to imitate the Apoſtles time, wold have the ſame form of diſcipline to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern whole Nations, as it did a chamberfull of men in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they wold make the ſame coat ſerve our Saviour at 30. yeers, which fitted him at three: Tis incredible how many ugly ſorts of hereſies they daily hatch, but they are moſt of them old ones newly furbiſh'd; they all relate to <hi>Aeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> a perfect hater of Biſhops, becauſe he could not be one himſelf. The two Sectaries which ſway moſt, are the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:117205:11"/>
and <hi>Independents,</hi> the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> is a ſpawn of a <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and the <hi>Independent</hi> a ſpawn of the <hi>Presbyterian:</hi> there's but one hop 'twixt the firſt and a <hi>Iew,</hi> and but half a hop 'twixt the other and an <hi>Infidell;</hi> they are both oppoſite to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy and Hierarchy; and the latter would have no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment at all, but a parity and promiſcuous confuſion, a race of creatures fit only to inhabit Hell: and one of the fruits of this bleſſed Parlement, and of theſe two Sectaries is that they have made more Jewes and Athieſts then I think there is in all Europe beſides; but truly my Lord I think the judgments of Heaven were never ſo viſible in any part of the Earth, as they are now here, for there is Rebell againſt Rebell, Houſe againſt Houſe, Cittie againſt Army, Parlement againſt Scot, but theſe two Sectaries, I mean the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent,</hi> who were the fire-brands that put this poor Iland firſt in a flame, are now in moſt deadly feud one againſt the other (though they both concur in this to deſtroy government:) And if the King had time enough to look only upon them, they would quickly hang, draw, and deſtroy one another.</p>
            <p>But indeed all Chriſtian Princes ſhold obſerve the motions &amp; ſucceſſes of theſe two unlucky Incendiaries, for if they ſhold ligue together againe (as they have often plaid faſt and looſe one with another) and prevail here, this Iland wold not terminate their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, they wold puzzle all the world beſides. Their Preachmen ordinarily cry out in the Pulpit, there is a great work to be done upon earth, for the reforming all mankind, and they are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Heaven to be the chief Inſtruments of bringing it about: They have already bin ſo buſie abroad, that (with vaſt ſommes of money) they brought the <hi>Swed</hi> upon the <hi>Dane,</hi> and the very Savages upon the Engliſh Cavalier in <hi>Virginia;</hi> and could they confederat with <hi>Turk,</hi> or <hi>Tartar,</hi> or Hell it ſelf againſt them, they wold do it: they are monſtrouſly puff'd up with pride, that they ſtick not to call themſelfs <hi>Conquerors;</hi> and one of the chief ring-leaders of them, an ignorant home-bred kind of <hi>Brewer,</hi> was not aſhamed to vaunt it publiquely in the Commons Houſe, that if he had but 20000. men, he wold undertake to march to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> and pull the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperour out of his throne.</p>
            <p>Touching the other grand Idoll the <hi>Parlement,</hi> 'tis true that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117205:12"/>
the primitive conſtitution of Parlement in this Iland was a wholſome peece of policy, becauſe it kept a good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and clos'd all ruptures 'twixt the King and his people, but this thing they call Parlement now, may rather be term'd but a cantle of one, or indeed a <hi>Conventicle</hi> of Schiſmatiques, rather then a great Counſell; 'tis like a kind of headleſſe Monſter, or ſom ectropiated carkas; for there is neither King nor Prelate, nor ſcarce the ſeventh part of Peers and Commons, no not the twelfth part fairely elected; nevertheleſſe they draw the peeple, ſpecially this City, like ſo many ſtupid animalls, to adore them.</p>
            <p>Yet though this inſtitution of Parlement be a wholſom thing in it ſelf, there is in my judgment a great incongruity in one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; and I believe it hath bin the cauſe of moſt diſtempers; It is, That the <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> are more in number then the <hi>Knights</hi> of <hi>Shires;</hi> for the <hi>Knights</hi> of the <hi>Shires</hi> are commonly Gentlemen well born, and bred, and vers'd in the Lawes of the Land, as well as forren governments, divers of them; but the <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> of Townes are commonly Tradeſmen, and being bred in Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, they are moſt of them inclining to Puritamiſm, and conſequently to popular government; theſe, exceeding the <hi>Knights</hi> in number, carry all before them by plurality of Voices, and ſo puzzle all: And now that I have mentioned <hi>Corporations,</hi> I muſt tell your Lordſhip, that the greateſt ſoloeciſm in the policy of this Kingdom, is the number of them; eſpecially this mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous City, which is compos'd of nothing els but of <hi>Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> and the greateſt errors that this King, ſpecially his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther committed, was to ſuffer this town to ſpread her wings ſo wide; for ſhe bears no proportion with the bi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe of the Iland, but may fit a Kingdom thrice as ſpacious; ſhe engroſſeth and dreines all the wealth and ſtrength of the Kingdom; ſo that I cannot compa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>England</hi> more properly then to one of our <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mona</hi> geeſe, where the cuſtom is, to fatten onely the heart, but in doing ſo the whole body growes lank.</p>
            <p>To draw to a concluſion, This Nation is in a moſt ſad and deſperate condition, that they deſerved to be pittied, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from ſinking, and having caſt the preſent ſtate of things and all intereſts into an equall balance, I find, my Lord there be three waies to do it, one good, and two bad:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:117205:12"/>1. The firſt of the bad ones is the <hi>Sword,</hi> which is one of the ſcourges of heaven, eſpecially the <hi>Civill ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond bad one is the Treaty, which they now offer the King in that ſmall Iland where he hath bin kept Captif ſo long, (in which quality the world will account him ſtill while he is detain'd there) and by that Treaty to bind him as faſt as they can, and not truſt him at all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The good way is, in a free confiding brave way (Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men-like to ſend for their King to London, where City, and Countrey ſhold petition him to ſummon a new and free full Parlement, which he may do as juſtly as ever he did thing in his life, theſe men having infring'd as well all the eſſentiall Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parlement, as ev'ry puntillio of it, for they have often riſen up in a confuſion without adjournment, they had two Speakers at once, they have moſt perjuriouſly and beyond all imagination betrayed the truſt both King and Countrey repos'd in them, ſubverted the very fundamentalls of all Law, and plung'd the whole Kingdom in this bottomleſſe gulf of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: another Parlement may happly do ſom good to this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Iland, and cure her convulſions, but for theſe men that arrogat to themſelfes the name of Parlement (by a locall puntil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio only becauſe they never ſtirr'd from the place where they have bin kept together by meer force) I find them by their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to be ſo pervers, ſo irrational and refractory, ſo far given over to a reprobat ſenſe, ſo fraught with rancor, with an irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable malice and thirſt of bloud, that <hi>England</hi> may well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire to be heal'd by ſuch Phlebotomiſts, or Quackſalvers; beſides they are ſo full of ſcruples, apprehenſions, and jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies proceeding from black guilty ſoules, and gawl'd conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they will do nothing but chop Logic with their King, and ſpin out time to continu their power, and evade puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they think is unavoydable if there ſhould be a free Parlement.</p>
            <p>Touching the King he comports himſelf with an admired temper'd equanimity, he invades and o'remaſters them more and more in all his anſwers by ſtrength of reaſon, though he have no ſoul breathing to conſult withall, but his owne Genius: he gaines wonderfully upon the hearts and opinion of his peeple,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117205:13"/>
and as the Sun uſeth to appear bigger in winter, and at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion in regard of the interpoſition of certain meteors 'twixt the eye of the beholder and the object, ſo this King being thus o'reclouded and declined ſhines far more glorious in the eyes of his peeple; and certainly theſe high morall vertues of conſtancy, courage and wiſdom com from above; and no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for Kings as they are elevated above all other peeple and ſtand upon higher ground, they ſooner receave the inſpirations of heaven; nor doth he only by ſtrength of reaſon outwit them, but he wooes them by gentlenes and manſuetude; as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of Paris who having an Ape in his houſe that had taken his only child out of the cradle, and dragged him up to the ridge of the houſe, the parent with ruthfull heart charmed the Ape by faire words and other blandiſhments to bring him ſoftly down, which he did; England may be ſaid to be now juſt upon ſuch a precipice, ready to have her braines daſht out, and I hope theſe men will not be worſe natur'd then that brute animal, but will ſave her.</p>
            <p>Thus have I given your Eminence a rough account of the ſtate of this poor and pittifully deluded peeple, which I wil perfect when I ſhall com to your preſence, which I hope will be before this Autumnall Equinox; I thought to have ſojourn'd here longer, but that I am growne weary of the clime, for I feare there s the other two ſcourge of heaven that menace this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, I mean the famin and peſtilence, eſpecially this City, for their prophanenes, rebellion and ſacriledge: it hath bin a talk a great while whether <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi> be com to the world or no, I am ſure <hi>Anti-Jeſus,</hi> which is worſe, is among this peeple, for they hold all veneration though voluntary proceeding from the inward motions of a ſweet devoted ſoule, and cauſing an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward genuflexion, to be ſuperſtitious, inſomuch that one of the Synodicall Saints here printed and publiſhed a Book entitling it againſt <hi>Ieſu Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London <date>this 16. of Auguſt, <hi>Stylo loci,</hi> 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>So in the profundeſt poſture of reverence I kiſſe your veſt, being My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Eminences moſt humbly devoted, <hi>J. B. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117205:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
